[Music]
Welcome to the 2025 release wave 1.
What's new in reporting for developers?
In this video, we have four different
topics to cover. New layout features in
AL, new layout features in the runtime
also for users. easier development of
reports with word layouts and and some
updated developer documentation. So
let's dive in. So the new things you can
do from AL from VS code when with report
layouts is that you can first of all
override any choice of Excel layout
multiple data sheets property that has
been set on the report. You can now set
that on the layout level. The second
thing is that you can now obsolete a
layout. Let me show you how. So here in
Visual Studio Code, I have a small
report al code. Um and um you notice
that I have a new layout called new
layout. And that's because I also have
an old layout here that I might want to
deprecate or obsolete. So uh so let's do
that first. Um and it's the same way as
you would deprecate any other thing in
AL. You simply set the obsolete tag to
something. Uh you set the obsolete state
and in this case we set it to pending
and obsolete reason. This obsolete is up
layout is obsolete because we have
something whatever obsolete tag is is
probably the version that you uh you use
for this. So let's put in something like
uh 20 28 whatever tags you use. So
that's the way you can obsolete a layout
from AL. The second thing is um that you
can
override the Excel multiple worksheets
property. So here I can simply say I
would like the Excel layout multiple
data sheets to be set to true even
though the Excel um layout multiple data
sheets might have been set to false on
the report. And the reason this is is
smart is that the default value for for
this property is false. So that that
means if you add a new layout to an
existing report, you can you can set
this Excel layout multiple data sheets
and therefore it's only your layout that
will have this property, not any any old
layouts uh that you might break that
customers have added. We also added some
new features when you use report layouts
in the report layouts page in the in the
application. There are three things.
First of all, you can set the Excel
layout multiple data sheets on the
layout level there as well as you could
in AL. There's also more visibility into
the properties of a layout. And finally,
you can validate a layout that either uh
that um that a customer or a
user added or even one that was added
from an extension or an app. Let's uh
dive in and take a
look. So here on the report layouts
page, you might notice a new menu called
layout. Here we have first of all
gathered some of the other old actions
um for layouts. But you can also see two
new actions validate and show layout
info. Before we dive into that, let me
just quickly show you in case you want
to add or a user wants to add Excel
layout to any report, maybe the number
series report here. Um, they can set
this multiple data sheets property
directly when they create a new layout.
So let's say test Excel, it's an Excel
layout. I can choose blank layout and
then I can choose multiple data sheets
and create um a new layout. So that's
the first
feature. The second thing is that you
might want to troubleshoot a layout. So
here we offer first of all the show
layout info. So that means you can ask a
user to provide everything about a
layout. Um there is the system ID is all
is in particularly useful if you have
telemetry because this system ID is also
the one that is locked to a custom
dimension called layout ID there. So you
can match the two and and see which of
the layouts that had a problem. You can
see um of course the type and you can
see for the last four parts here um who
created or modified the layout
especially and this is only uh populated
these properties only populated for
layouts that users uh import or work
with not the ones that are provided from
extensions or
apps. You also notice that um you can
see the obsolete property if any layouts
have been obsoleted that's shown here.
You can see the last modified date and
the last modified by here on the list.
So that's an just an easy way for you to
see those properties. And finally uh
from this layout menu there's also this
new validate action. So I can validate
any layout uh whether there's anything
wrong. Uh I don't have any layouts with
problems. So this layout is valid. Um
for now for the
26.0 the the first major release is only
RDL layout that will be validated in a
next minor. Uh we will also add
validation for word and excel.
We also made it a lot easier to work
with reports that involve word layouts
and that is both for new reports and for
existing reports where you want to add a
word
layout. Similarly to the Excel layout
feature, you can now find
um standard information about the report
metadata and the requests directly in
the XML for the for for the word uh
report for word uh layout. And that
makes it first of all much easier
because you don't have to code this in
AL for a new report. But also for
existing reports if um you can
standardize the way you show report name
or company name and other things so that
anyone using the layout will just know
that this is where you get that
information. Let's dive into into Word
and take a look. Imagine that you want
to add a new word layout to an existing
report in Business Central. Let's take
uh the number series report. The current
version here only have uh one report
layout which is of type RDLC and we want
to add a more modern layout type. So
let's take uh here and say this is
number series word and I want to add a
word layout here and I want to create a
new blank layout. So let's create this.
Okay. So I'll export
this and get it
downloaded. And now I will open it in
word and let's take a look what's
happening now. So here in word I um will
choose the developer menu and the XML
mapping pane and here I will choose the
the metadata for the report. There you
go. Now normally you can see um that you
have the report data item columns here.
We're not going to dive into that.
Instead you see a new kit on the block
here. BC report information. If I expand
this, there are new two new types of
data available. The first is
uh the metadata from the report where
it's coming from uh what's the report
name uh the about title about text
report help and maybe I want to use the
report name and put that here into the
report layout.
And uh the second part here is the
requests metadata. Here I can see things
like which environment, which company,
company display name, which user uh when
the report was rendered in which
language and also uh instead of the date
and time when it was rendered, I can
also easily get a hierarchy of year,
month, day, hour and minute. So maybe I
want to see that uh or I want to put
into my layout the year somewhere here
maybe in the
header and maybe I want to take
the month number here and now I can
construct
uh the the date and maybe the day as
well. So and I can construct
uh that in any any format I like. Um and
uh similarly maybe the company display
name. Let's put that in as
well. And of course you would then use
all the other properties or the columns
from the report uh data set down here.
But notice that the things that were
previously coded here such as company
name and maybe user uh name and so on,
you don't have to use that anymore. Uh
you can just use them in a standard
fashion. So, let's uh save this and get
back to Business Central and import it
and see what it looks like. Back in
Business Central on the report layouts
page, I will now use the replace layout
action and put in my new version of the
layout. Here we go. And let's let's run
it and see what
happens. And hopefully you will we will
get these new properties from from these
uh system generated data items. So let's
take a look. And there we go. So you see
the report name, the year, the month,
and the date. So this recording was
apparently done on the 2nd of March
2025. And this is the company display
name that I put into the
layout. The final part in the developer
video here is about uh some updated
developer documentation for especially
for obsoleting reports. So you can
always go to the
aka.ms/bcde developer to get to the
developer documentation and then you
need to go to the reporting or you can
just search for obsoleting reports.
Let's try that. So I followed the AKA
link for the developer documentation and
um the things about reporting is here
under programming in AL language and
then down here under developing reports
but we just want to find the
obsolate
reports new article. So that's here and
um what this is is a guideline both for
obsoleting report layouts but also how
you can obsolete reports in general. Now
of course this is nothing new as a
developer. You could just put in the
obsolete um properties but how do you
communicate the change to a user? And
that's what this um documentation al is
all about. Uh how could you how can you
tell the user when they use tell me when
they use the request page when they use
the help pane or maybe when they show
use if they use the report layouts page
or the report uh layout picker from the
request page. So and also there's some
guidance of how you can track the usage
of your doc deprecated or obsoleted uh
reports with telemetry. So, go check
that out in the developer documentation.
And um in here there's a ton of
different articles about how to how to
work with with reports and layouts. So,
you might want to revisit the
documentation in case new articles came
in since last time you saw it.